Guide to the William Pitt Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Pitt collection
1758-1806
GEN MSS 442
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
Correspondence, writings, and other papers that document the lives and work of William Pitt, Earl of Chatham (1708-1778) and his son, William Pitt (1759-1806). Correspondents include John Murray, Duke of Atholl;George Nugent Temple Grenville, Marquess of Buckingham; Philip Yorke, Earl of Hardwicke; and George William Frederick Osborne, Duke of Leeds.
Pitt, William, Earl of Chatham, 1708-1778
Pitt, William, 1759-1806
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederick W. Hilles in memory of Bernhard Knollenberg, 1974.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
WILLIAM PITT, EARL OF CHATHAM (1708-1778)
Born in London on 15 November 1708, "the elder Pitt," as William Pitt was known, was the son of Robert Pitt and Lady Harriet Villiers. He was educated at Eton and Trinity College, Oxford, and in 1735 entered parliament for Old Sarum, one of the boroughs controlled by his brother. He became secretary of state in 1756, where he was determined to continue and increase military action against France during the Seven Years War. Opposition from King George II forced him to resign a year later, but public support brought him back only a few months later. He was forced to resign again in 1761, when the cabinet refused to support a war with Spain. In 1766 he established a new ministry, but his health prevented him from serving any real function, and he resigned in 1768. Pitt died on 11 May 1778.
WILLIAM PITT (1759-1806)
William Pitt was born in Kent, England on 28 May 1759, son of William Pitt, Earl of Chatham, and Lady Hester Grenville. He was educated at home as a child, and at age fourteen attended Pembroke Hall, Cambridge. In 1780, he was called to the bar, and joined the western assize circuit. He failed to win a parliamentary seat at Cambridge in 1780, but in 1781 he was elected to a seat for Appleby in Westmorland. In July of 1782, he became Chancellor of the Exchequer. He became the leader of the Commons in the ministry of William Petty, Earl of Shelburne, defeating Charles James Fox, with whom he began a lifelong rivalry. After the failure of the ministries of Shelburne and his successor, William Henry Cavendish-Bentinck, Duke of Portland, Pitt became Britain's youngest Prime Minister at the age of twenty-four. His seventeen-year term saw the reduction of the national debt, the union of England with Ireland, and the defeat of the invading French at Trafalgar. He died heavily in debt in 1806.
Scope and Contents
The William Pitt Collection contains correspondence, writings and other papers that document the lives and work of William Pitt, Earl of Chatham (1708-1778) and his son, William Pitt (1759-1806). The collection has been arranged into two series, Correspondence and Other Papers.
Series I, Correspondence, contains letters to and from both William Pitt the elder and the younger. Also included are third party letters.
Series II, Other Papers, contains six texts, the authorship of which is undetermined, except the first, which has been attributed to Mr. Franklyn.
Atholl, John Murray, Duke of, 1755-1830; Buckingham, George Nugent Temple Grenville, Marquess of, 1753-1813; Hardwicke, Philip Yorke, Earl of, 1690-1764; Leeds, George William Frederick Osborne, Duke of, 1775-1856; Pitt, William, Earl of Chatham, 1708-1778; Pitt, William, 1759-1806
- Correspondence, 1758-1806; Series I; 0.30' (3/4 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into three subseries: William Pitt, Earl of Chatham (1708-1778); William Pitt (1759-1806); and Third Party Letters.
  - WILLIAM PITT, EARL OF CHATHAM (1708-1778)
    - Outgoing
      - Bristol, George William Hervey, Earl of (extracts and originals), 1758, 1760 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Read, W. and E. Charlton, 1759 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Stanley, Hans (extract of letter), 1761 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Incoming
      - Abreu, Félix de (copies and originals), 1758-59 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Bedford, John Russell, Duke of (1710-1771), 1759 Sep 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Carteret, John, Earl Granville, 1761 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Dover, Joseph Yorke, Baron, 1759 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Frankland, [Thomas, Sir?], 1759 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Hardwicke, Philip Yorke, Earl of (1690-1764), 1759-60 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Hawke, Edward Hawke, Baron, 1760 Dec 21 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Porten, Stanier, Sir, 1760 Apr 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Stanley, Hans, 1761 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - WILLIAM PITT (1759-1806)
    - Outgoing
      - Aldborough, [Edward Stratford, Earl of?], 1785 Aug 30 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Courtney, Lord, 1785 Sep 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Lisburn, Sharman, Lt. Col. (draft), 1783 Aug 11 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Miles, [William Augustus?], 1785 Dec 23 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Molloy, Captain, 1785 Oct 27 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Sackville, [George Germain, Viscount] (draft), 1783 Dec 29 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Incoming
      - Atholl, John Murray, Duke of (1755-1830), 1787-97 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Auckland, William Eden, Baron, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Buckingham, George Nugent Temple Grenville, Marquess of, 1783-85, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Carmarthen, Marquis of
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: George William Frederick Osborne, Duke of Leeds, box 1, folder 24
      - Castlereagh, Robert Stewart, Viscount (copy), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Cooke, Edward (fragment), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Leeds, George William Frederick Osborne, Duke of, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Miles, William Augustus, 1785 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Newcastle, Henry Fienness Pelham- Clinton, Duke of (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Orde, Thomas, Baron Bolton, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Portland, William Henry Cavendish- Bentinck, Duke of (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Redesdale, John Mitford, Baron, 1800 Jul 7 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Rous, George, [n.y.] Mar 26 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Rutland, Charles Manners, Duke of, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Sackville, George Germain, Viscount, 1783 Dec 31 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Teignmouth, John Shore, Baron, 1798 Jan 31 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - "G. R.", 1785 Nov 4 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Precis of letters received by Mr. Pitt, 1793-1806 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - THIRD PARTY LETTERS
    - Carmarthen, Marquis of
    - Leeds, George William Frederick Osborne, Duke of
      - To Mr. Crawford, 1785 Nov 4 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - To Sir David Dalrymple, 1785 Sep 30 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - To James Harris, Earl of Malmesbury (copy), 1785 Dec 16 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - To Charles Lennox, Duke of Richmond and Lennox[?] (copy), 1785 Dec 27 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - From Sir David Dalrymple (extracts, copies, and originals), 1785 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - From James Harris, Earl of Malmesbury, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - From Mr. Walpole (extract of letter), 1785 Dec 3 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Others
      - Munro, Al. to Mr. Woodford (extract of letters), 1785 Nov 24 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - Price, Richard to William Petty, [Marquis of Lansdowne?], 1782 Aug 6 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - St. Helens, Alleyne Fitzherbert, Baron to Lord Grantham (copy), 1783 Mar 13 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - Southwell, [Richard Hayes?] to General Grenville, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - Wright, James, Sir to Anthony Addington (copy), 1778 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Other Papers, 1760-1785; Series II; 0.10' (1/4 box)
  - Franklyn, ----. "On Parliamentary Reform," manuscript, 1785 Jun 17 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Annotated: "from Mr. [Wyvill?]."
  - Unidentified
    - "Observations respecting Ireland," manuscript, 1785 Nov 22 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - "Postscript to the short conversation of yesterday," manuscript, 1760 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - "Precis of Sir T. Gray's letters [to Mr. Pitt]," manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - "Precis of such parts of the dispatch from Spain as has not been read by the King," manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - "Short remarks on the Institution of the Wine Company in Portugal," manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 53)